Benjamin Helm Bristow Papers
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress
Benjamin Helm Bristow Papers 1839-1932 (bulk 1874-1896)
MSS13862
Bristow, Benjamin Helm, 1832-1896
16,000 items
20 containers
7.2 linear feet
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress Washington, D.C.
Army officer, lawyer, United States secretary of the treasury, and solicitor general. Correspondence, speeches, biographical material, newspaper clippings, pamphlets, other printed material, and photographs relating primarily to Bristow's service as solicitor general and secretary of the treasury in the administrations of Ulysses S. Grant and to his New York City law firm. Includes a letterpress book of incoming and outgoing correspondence of the commissioner of internal revenue concerning the whiskey frauds of 1875.
Selected Search Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the LC Catalog. They are grouped by name of person or organization, by subject or location, and by occupation and listed alphabetically.
People
Belknap, William W. (William Worth), 1829-1890--Correspondence.; Blaine, James Gillespie, 1830-1893--Correspondence.; Boynton, Henry V. (Henry Van), 1835-1905--Correspondence.; Bristow, Benjamin Helm, 1832-1896.; Childs, George William, 1829-1894--Correspondence.; Davis, David, 1815-1886--Correspondence.; Drexel, Anthony J. (Anthony Joseph), 1826-1893--Correspondence.; Edmunds, George F. (George Franklin), 1828-1919--Correspondence.; Fish, Hamilton, 1808-1893--Correspondence.; Goodloe, William Cassius, 1841-1889--Correspondence.; Grant, Ulysses S. (Ulysses Simpson), 1822-1885--Correspondence.; Grant, Ulysses S. (Ulysses Simpson), 1822-1885.; Harlan, John Marshall, 1833-1911--Correspondence.; Meriwether, W. A.--Correspondence.; Porter, Horace, 1837-1921--Correspondence.; Swayne, Noah Haynes, 1804-1884--Correspondence.
Organizations
United States. Department of the Treasury. Office of the Secretary.; United States. Office of Commissioner of Internal Revenue.; United States. Solicitor General.
Subjects
Law--United States.; Practice of law--New York (State)--New York.; Whiskey fraud.
Places
United States--Economic policy--To 1933.; United States--Politics and government--1865-1900.
Occupations
Army officers.; Cabinet officers.; Lawyers.; Public officials.
Provenance
The papers of Benjamin Helm Bristow, army officer, lawyer, United States secretary of the treasury, and solicitor general, were deposited in the Library of Congress by William B. Bristow in 1937 and converted to a gift in 1946.
Access and Restrictions
The papers of Benjamin Helm Bristow are open to research. Researchers are advised to contact the Manuscript Reading Room prior to visiting. Many collections are stored off-site and advance notice is needed to retrieve these items for research use.
Biographical Note
Date Event
1832 Born, Elkton, Ky.
1851 Graduated, Jefferson College, Washington, Pa.
1853 Admitted to Kentucky bar after studying law with his father, Francis Bristow, congressman from Kentucky.
1861 1865 Officer in Kentucky infantry and Kentucky calvary; wounded at the Battle of Shiloh (1863) and assisted in the capture of John Hunt Morgan during his raid through Indiana and Ohio (July 1863)
1863 1865 Kentucky state senator
1865 1866 Assistant United States attorney
1866 1870 United States district attorney for Louisville, Ky., district
1870 1872 First solicitor general of the United States
1874 1876 Secretary of the treasury Reorganized Treasury Department and successfully prosecuted the ?Whiskey Ring? accused of defrauding the federal government of tax revenue
1876 Candidate for Republican Party nomination for president
1878 Began law practice in New York
1896, June 22 Died, New York, N.Y.
Scope and Content Note
The papers of Benjamin Helm Bristow (1832-1896) span the years 1839-1932, with the bulk of the material from 1874 to 1896. The collection consists of correspondence, speeches, biographical material, newspaper clippings, pamphlets, other printed materials, and photographs relating primarily to Bristow's service as solicitor general and secretary of the treasury in President Ulysses S. Grant's administrations and to his New York City law firm. Included are a letterpress book of incoming and outgoing correspondence of the commissioner of internal revenue concerning the whiskey frauds of 1875.
Among the correspondents are William W. Belknap, James Gillespie Blaine, Henry V. Boynton, George William Childs, David Davis, Anthony Joseph Drexel, George F. Edmunds, Hamilton Fish (1808-1893), William Cassius Goodloe, Ulysses S. Grant, John Marshall Harlan, W. A. Meriwether, Horace Porter, and Noah Haynes Swayne.
Arrangement of the Papers
This collection is arranged by type of material.
Container List
- Correspondence (Box 1)
  - Dec. 1839-Dec. 1871 (Box 1)
  - 1872-1873 (Box 2)
  - Jan.-Oct. 1874 (Box 3)
  - Nov. 1874-Mar. 1875 (Box 4)
  - Apr.-Aug. 1875 (Box 5)
  - Sept.-Dec. 1875 (Box 6)
  - 1876-1877 (Box 7)
  - 1878-1893, undated (Box 8)
  - Speeches and biographical material (Box 8)
  - Treasury reports and related matter (Box 8)
  - Photograph of Bristow (Box 8)
- Letterbooks (Box 9)
  - Vols. 1-3, June 1872-1874 (Box 9)
  - Vols. 4-6, July 1874-Feb. 1875 (Box 10)
  - Vols. 7-9, Mar. 1875-May 1882 (Box 11)
  - Vols. 10-12, May 1882-May 1896 (Box 12)
  - Private, Apr.-June 1876 (Box 13)
  - Copies of letters received and sent by the commissioner of internal revenue related to whisky frauds in St. Louis, Mo., Chicago, Ill., and Milwaukee, Wis. (Box 13)
- Record of correspondence in the office of solicitor of the treasury relating to the detection and prosecution of defrauders of revenue on distilled liquors (Box 14)
- Newspapers and clippings (Box 15)
- Scrapbooks (Box 16)
  - Vols. 1-2, June 1874-1876 (Box 16)
  - Vol. 3, July 1876-June 1896 (Box 17)
- Other printed matter (Box 18)
  - Memorial of Bristow (Box 18)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 18)
- Photographs and steel engravings (Box 19)
- Negative photostats and letters (Box 20)
  - 1839-1876 (Box 20)
  - 1875-1887 (Box 20)